Gregg Smith Papers
Gregg Smith Papers
circa 1950-2018
Smith, Gregg.
35 linear ft.
American composer and choral conductor and founder of the award-winning choral group The Gregg Smith Singers. Collection includes handwritten and annotated original scores, parts, reductions, drafts, and compositional sketches; published music; correspondence, date books, programs, and memorabilia; and a few audio recordings.
5303457
Biographical History
Gregg Smith (1931-2016) was an American composer and choral conductor who exerted a profound influence on American choral music.
Born in Chicago, he studied music at the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) where he earned a bachelor's (1954) and master's degree (1956). He founded a number of choral groups, associations, and festivals, including the Gregg Smith Singers in 1955, a Grammy Award-winning group "renowned for its rich vocal blend, flawless intonation and clarity" which continues to record and perform both nationally and internationally; the Long Island Symphonic Choral Association (LISCA) in 1968, which he led for 40 years; and the Adirondack Festival of American Music (1973), held annually for more than 30 years. A prolific composer, Smith produced more than 400 works for chorus, orchestra, and the theater and was the composer in residence for St. Peter's Church in Manhattan from 1988. He also taught, serving as head of the choral program at Ithaca College for many years.
According to Dennis Keene, artistic director of the Voices of Ascension Chorus and Orchestra and for many years an organist with the Gregg Smith Singers, Smith was "one of the biggest chapters in American choral history. His dedication to the American music of his own time was unparalleled. It is no exaggeration to say that he did more than anyone to promote and support contemporary American choral composition."
[Biographical sketch adapted from Smith's obituary in the New York Times, 15 Jul 2016.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Gregg Smith Papers consists of compositions, correspondence, memorabilia, and published material. Taken as a whole, the collection provides an overview of the creative output of one of America's most prolific composers.
Compositions form the vast majority of the collection. In the donor's inventory provided with the collection, compositions were divided into five categories; these categories have been retained with the exception of splitting out Operas into a separate series. Descriptions of material in the inventory below have, with minor edits for consistency, been taken almost entirely from that inventory.
Large orchestral/choral works contains larger, longer, and/or more complex compositions. Earth Requiem, for example, a one-hour piece commissioned by the Cathedral Choral Society of Washington DC in 1997, has 22 movements; calls for a large chorus, symphony orchestra, solo quartet and children's choir; and takes its text not only from the Latin Requiem Mass but also from poems by Walt Whitman and e e cummings, and Iroquois and Navajo prayers. Beware of the Soldier was written for George Bragg and the Texas Boys Choir in May of 1969; Smith described it as
...a reflection of two aspects of mankind — childhood and innocence (as exemplified by those wonderful music-making boys) and 'manhood' and the warrior complex (the male chorus). There is a third important element which focuses the above toward the futility of war -- that of the elegies (sung by a solo voice).
[Quote taken from liner notes for New World Records LP.] Other compositions in this series include magnificats, madrigals, and pieces based on numerous American poets and writers.
Large symphonic works, Christmas and folk contains choral arrangements of traditional carols and holiday church music (Festival of Carols, Suite of Antiphonal Carols) as well as Smith's Jazz Mass for St. Peter's and a choral arrangement of the Peace Prayer of St. Francis. Also in this series are pieces based on American folk songs, such as Festival of Folks Songs and Old Folks Quadrille (based on the music of Stephen Foster).
Operas contains original operas, operettas, or musicals by Smith. In some cases Smith created both text and music (The Other Wise Man, Rip Van Winkle) while others were a collaboration, with someone else writing the lyrics and libretto -- for example, the song cycle Pretty Good Company was based on the epigrams of Rosalind Smith's cousin Gomer Rees. Smith often collaborated with friend and poet Kim Rich.
Orchestral/choral works, miscellaneous contains smaller and/or less complex pieces. A wide range of styles and source material are represented, including classical (Brass Quintet, Shakespeare madrigals), sacred (Gloria for Two Choirs, Offertorium, Exultate Deo), American poetry (A Child's Garden of Verses), folk songs of many countries (England, Israel, Jamaica, Wales), and Native American (a choral setting of Chief Seattle's famous speech in 1854).
Popular song arrangements and compositions contains Smith's arrangements of popular works by others. Included here are settings of pieces by Nat King Cole, Stephen Foster, George Gershwin, Stephen Sondheim, Rodgers and Hammerstein, and Victor Herbert.
Unpublished choral manuscripts contains a variety of pieces in various stages of completion. As with the other series, many different styles and source materials are represented: traditional songs (I ride old paint, Es ist ein schnee gefallen, B'rohos shel Hanukah); sacred music (psalms, hymns, etc.), poems and writings by American and other authors (Five Sandburg songs, Mark Twain madrigals); and events of the day (Election of 1968, 9/11/2001). There are also a few purely instrumental piece such as "Fugetto for solo sax" and "Suite for harp."
Correspondence is mostly with publishers (Earthsongs, Schirmer) and individuals at various recording companies (e.g., John McClure of Columbia Records). Much of it relates to a European tour in 1967, which encompassed the recording of several pieces in Zurich for CBS records.
Memorabilia contains calendars and itineraries spanning more than 20 years, along with clippings, programs, and receipts/expenses from tours in the US, the Far East, and Scandinavia. Of particular interest is a set of drawings and poems created by the Adirondack Children's Chorus in 1995, as a gift to Smith for his many years of work with them. Smith later adapted the poems into a new choral work, Adirondack Children's Songs (1997).
Published octavos contains Smith's library of published editions of his work. Some are marked and/or include questions from the publisher, corrections, annotations, notes, etc.
Arrangement of the Collection
Series are arranged alphabetically by title. Compositions are subdivided by type, as detailed above, and within each type are arranged alphabetically by title. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by type. Published octavos are alphabetical by title.
Related Material
See also the
Gregg Smith Singers Recordings
and the
Gregg Smith Singers Collection
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Music; New York State; Biggs, E. Power (Edward Power), 1906-1977.; Hill, Paul, 1933 May 8-; McClure, John.; Norton, Kim Rich.; Smith, Gregg.; Adirondack children's choir.; Gregg Smith Singers.; Gregg Smith Vocal Quartet.; Texas Boys' Choir.; Earth requiem.; Jazz mass for Saint Peter's.; Choruses, Secular (Mixed voices); Composers -- United States.; Choral conductors -- United States.; Choral music -- United States.; Folk music -- United States.; Audiocassettes.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Compact discs.; Floppy discs.; Librettos (documents for music); Programs (documents); Scores (documents for music); Sound recordings.; Composers.; Conductors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Rosalind Rees Smith, 2019.
Inventory
- Compositions
  - Large orchestral/choral works
    - Aesop's Fables
      - Full score, pianists copy (Oversize 1)
      - Full score, reprinted and bound (Oversize 1)
      - Full score, vellum (Oversize 1)
      - Miscellaneous vellum sketches and alternative pages (Oversize 1)
    - Bach Variations
      - Full score, computer printout (Oversize 1)
      - Full score with conductor's marks (Oversize 3)
      - Full score with marked revisions (Oversize 1)
      - Full score, bound, incomplete (end at m. 215) (Oversize 1)
      - Full score for 2 pianos, vellums (Oversize 3)
      - Full orchestral score, conductor's score (Oversize 3)
      - Full orchestral score, vellums (Oversize 3)
      - Parts, computer printout, wind only, flute, oboe, English horn, bassoon (Oversize 2)
      - Parts, copied, flute, oboe, clarinet, English horn, bassoon (Oversize 2)
      - Parts, handwritten, flute, oboe, clarinet, bassoon, violin, viola, cello, string bass (Oversize 2)
      - Piano vocal score, copied; choral piano score with notations (Oversize 2)
    - Beware the soldier, sections include Songs of War, Songs of Innocence, and Elegies
      - Full score used to edit recordings (fragile) (Oversize 2)
      - Full score with conductor's markings (Oversize 2)
      - Full score with original signature and conductor's markings (Oversize 4)
      - Full score, vellum (Oversize 4)
      - Elegy, vocal piano reductions, vellum (Oversize 4)
      - Men's chorus with piano reductions, vellum and copies for War is sacred, Blossom, The man and the angel, A thousand captains (Oversize 4)
      - Songs of Innocence, vellums (partial) (Oversize 4)
      - Parts, vellum (Oversize 4)
      - Parts, copied, 2 folders (Oversize 4)
    - Canticles of Praise
      - Director's score with markings, bound (Oversize 5)
      - Full score with director's markings, includes 3 different markups of "Finale" (Oversize 5)
      - Full score with accompanist's markings (Oversize 5)
      - Full score, vellums (Oversize 5)
      - Madrigal choir score (Oversize 5)
      - Parts, handwritten, bells, chime, organ (Oversize 5)
      - Accompanist's libretto with markings; director's soloist sheet and libretto (Oversize 5)
      - Tenor soloist's score, bound (Oversize 5)
      - Miscellaneous fragments, Swan Sequence and Finale (computer printouts with markings, plus copy of 1 ms page for Swan), Celeste and Epiphany Prelude (vellums) (Oversize 5)
    - Concord Hymn
      - Full score, handwritten (Oversize 6)
      - Full score, copy (Oversize 6)
      - Full score, copy, with revisions and sketches (Oversize 7)
      - Choral vocal score, copy, bound (Oversize 7)
      - Choral vocal score, vellums (Oversize 7)
      - Parts, handwritten (Oversize 7)
      - Parts, copy (Oversize 7)
    - A Congregation of canons
      - Full score with conductor's marks (Oversize 7)
      - Full score, bound and unmarked (Oversize 3)
      - Full score, vellum and mini-vellum (Oversize 7)
      - Full score, singer's copy, bound (Oversize 7)
      - Parts, vellum (Oversize 7)
      - Parts, copies, violin, viola, cello, clarinet (Oversize 7)
    - The Continental Harmonist [noted in donor inventory as "A work in process for publication"]
      - Full orchestral score ("Master Conductor's Score"), handwritten, with conducting and composition marks (Oversize 6)
      - Full orchestral score, copy, with conductor's marks (Oversize 8)
      - Full score for 2 pianos and choir, vellums (Oversize 8)
      - Full score for 2 pianos and choir, copy (Oversize 6)
      - Parts, handwritten (Oversize 8)
      - Parts sketches (Oversize 8)
    - Dedication: Theme + Variation on a Lutheran Hymn
      - Full score, vellums (Oversize 8)
      - Full conductor's score, bound (Oversize 8)
      - Parts, vellums (Oversize 8)
    - Divertimento
      - Full score, bound (Oversize 8)
      - Full score, bound, with pianists markings (Oversize 9)
    - Earth Requiem
      - Full score, computer printout, bound (Oversize 10)
      - Full score, computer printout, bound and marked (Oversize 39)
      - Children's chorus score, computer printout, bound (Box 1)
      - Piano vocal score, computer printout, bound and prepped for publication, includes note to Gomer Rees (Box 1)
      - Parts, computer printout, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Parts, computer printout with revisions for publication, in 3-ring binder (Box 2)
      - Piano vocal score, computer printout, marked, in 3-ring binder (Box 2)
      - Piano vocal score, computer printout, marked, in 3-ring binder, noted in donor inventory as "early draft for publication" (Box 2)
      - Table of contents for programs, draft (Box 1)
    - Festive Song
      - Full orchestral score, handwritten (Oversize 3)
      - Full score, piano and vocal (Oversize 9)
      - Parts, handwritten (incomplete), flute, clarinet, oboe, bassoon, horn, English horn (Oversize 9)
    - Four Concord Chorales
      - Full score, bound (Oversize 9)
      - Full score, copy, with conductor's marks (Oversize 9)
      - Parts [copy 1] (Oversize 9)
      - Parts [copy 2] (Oversize 9)
    - How Bright is the day
      - Full score, computer printout (Oversize 11)
    - The Lion and the Unicorn
      - Full score, vellums (Oversize 11)
      - Full score, copy, and copy of text from book (Oversize 11)
      - Parts, violin, handwritten (Oversize 11)
    - Lullaby
      - Full score, handwritten (Oversize 6)
      - Full score, copy, with conductor's markings (Oversize 6)
      - Parts, handwritten (Oversize 11)
      - Parts, copied (Oversize 11)
      - Piano score, copy (Oversize 11)
      - Piano vocal score, vellum and paper, with notes used for orchestration and autograph (Oversize 11)
    - Magnificat, Holly Hutcheson
      - Organ vocal score (Oversize 11)
    - Magnificat, Raymond Moreman
      - Full score, vellum (Oversize 12)
      - Full score, bound, missing last page (Oversize 40)
      - Parts, vellums (Oversize 11)
      - Parts, copied and marked (Oversize 11)
      - Piano vocal score, copy of manuscript (Oversize 11)
    - Magnificat I
      - Full score, handwritten (Oversize 10)
      - Full orchestral score, copied (Oversize 13)
      - Full orchestral score, copied, bound and marked, removed from binder; note in donor inventory reads, "all orchestral scores end on pg 5 of last movement. Continue to end of piece using choral vocal score" (Oversize 13)
        See also Memorabilia: Binder for original binder.
      - Parts, vellums (Oversize 13)
      - Parts, handwritten (Oversize 13)
      - Parts, copied [set A], includes a few handwritten pages; 3 folders (Oversize 13)
      - Parts, copied [set B], 3 folders (Oversize 14)
      - Piano vocal score, vellums (Oversize 14)
      - Piano vocal score, copied (Box 1)
      - Piano vocal score, copied and bound (Box 1)
    - A Modicum of Madrigals
      - 2. Silver Swan and 3. Falala, vellums (Oversize 15)
      - 2. Silver Swan and 3. Falala, piano vocal score, copies (Oversize 15)
    - O Magnum Mysterium
      - Full score, with conductor's marks and additional edited pg 10 (Oversize 15)
      - Full score, vellums, missing last page (Oversize 15)
    - On the Beach at Night
      - Full score, handwritten (Oversize 15)
      - Parts, computer printout (Oversize 15)
    - Papa Bach
      - Full score, bound (Oversize 15)
      - Full score, vellums (Oversize 15)
      - Libretto, typescript and copy (Oversize 15)
    - Peter Quince at the piano
      - Piano vocal score, vellums (Oversize 15)
      - Piano vocal score, copy, bound (Oversize 15)
    - Psalms of Joy
      - Full score with markings, last page of Psalm 95 missing (Oversize 12)
      - Full score of Psalm 95, copy (Oversize 12)
      - Parts, brass, copies (Oversize 12)
      - Piano vocal of Psalm 100, computer printout (Oversize 12)
      - Piano vocal for Psalms 23, 4, and 100, copied and bound (Oversize 12)
      - Miscellaneous extra copies of various pages (Oversize 12)
    - Reflections and Transformations
      - Full score, vellums (Oversize 15)
      - Full score, handcopied by USAF personnel (Oversize 15)
      - Full score, copy, bound (Oversize 15)
    - Revolutionary Suite
      - Full orchestral score, handwritten, with conducting and composition marks (Oversize 16)
      - Parts, handwritten (Oversize 16)
      - Miscellaneous, includes copies of pieces by Francis Hopkinson Smith and others (Oversize 16)
    - Seasons of Love
      - Full score, vellums (Oversize 14)
      - Full score, copied and bound (Box 1)
      - Full score, copied, marked and bookmarked (Oversize 14)
      - Full score, copied, incomplete (Oversize 14)
      - LISCA notes, list of songs/movements (Box 1)
    - Secular Canticle
      - Director's score, bound (Oversize 16)
      - Full score, vellums (Oversize 16)
      - Full score, copy, bound (Oversize 16)
      - Parts, violin and oboe (Oversize 16)
      - Piano score, handwritten copy, bound (Oversize 16)
    - Sonorities
      - Full conductor's score, bound (Oversize 16)
      - Full score, copies in two sizes (Oversize 16)
    - Spring Songs
      - Full score, handwritten (Oversize 16)
      - Full score, handwritten copy (Oversize 16)
      - Full orchestral score, final computer printout, bound (Oversize 17)
      - Parts, computer printout (Oversize 17)
      - Piano vocal score, handwritten (Oversize 17)
      - Piano vocal score, draft, computer printout photocopy with notes (incomplete) (Oversize 17)
      - Piano vocal score, final, computer printout bound (Oversize 17)
      - Texts, and notes (Oversize 17)
    - Steps
      - Full score, bound and unmarked (Oversize 17)
      - Full score, miniature (Oversize 17)
      - Full score, original, with Dave Starobin's markings (Oversize 17)
      - Full score, vellums (Oversize 17)
    - Street Cries of NY
      - Full score, vellums (Oversize 17)
      - Full score, copied (Oversize 17)
    - A Time to Every Purpose
      - Full score, handwritten with conductor's notes (Oversize 12)
      - Full score, copied from vellums, bound (Oversize 17)
      - Parts, handwritten (Oversize 17)
    - To Reach for the Stars / High Flight
      - Full orchestration, handwritten (unfinished) (Oversize 18)
      - Full score, vellum (Oversize 18)
      - Full score, copied, bound, includes copy of article with poem "High Flight" by John Gillespie, from which text was taken (Oversize 18)
      - Parts, vellum, violin only (Oversize 18)
    - Two Whitman songs
      - Full scores, handwritten, 2 folders (Oversize 12)
      - Full scores, computer printouts, 2 folders (Oversize 18)
      - Partial scores, with notes from Dale Jergenson (Oversize 18)
      - Texts, original poems photocopied from Leaves of Grass; miscellaneous pages, possibly from a published edition (Oversize 18)
  - Large symphonic works, Christmas and folk
    - America the Beautiful
      - Full score, handwritten; vocal score, copy; piano-vocal score, copy (Oversize 40)
    - Angels from the Realms of Glory
      - Choral manuscript, copies (Oversize 19)
    - Coplas
      - Full score, vellums, includes string bass part, 1 pg (Oversize 19)
      - Full score, 2 copies, 1 with marks (Oversize 19)
      - Full score, computer printout (Oversize 19)
    - A Festival of Carols
      - Conductor's score, copied with marks (Oversize 19)
      - Full score, 1st movement, 3 copies, 1 bound (Oversize 40)
      - Full score, 1st movement, copy (reduced size) (Oversize 19)
      - Parts, handwritten, 2 folders (Oversize 19)
      - Parts, 1st movement, copies (Oversize 19)
      - Parts, Babe of Bethlehem, copies (Oversize 19)
      - Parts, Greensleeves, copies (Oversize 19)
      - Miscellaneous, misc copies, 2 handwritten sketches (Oversize 19)
    - Festival of Folk Songs, note in donor inventory reads, "some sketches of these works are also in...the misc. arrangements folder"
      - All Through the Night, full score, handwritten and copy; parts, handwritten; choral score, partial; melody and treble arr. for boy and bell choirs (Oversize 20)
      - Ash Grove, full score, copies; parts, handwritten; miscellaneous sketches, handwritten (Oversize 20)
      - Black is the color of my true love's hair, full score, copy; parts, handwritten (Oversize 20)
      - La Cicirinella, parts, handwritten; printed copy (Oversize 20)
      - Drunken Sailor, full score, handwritten copy; parts, handwritten; choral score, copy (partial) (Oversize 20)
      - Edelweiss, full score, handwritten copy; parts, handwritten (Oversize 20)
      - Froggy went a-courtin', full score, handwritten copy (Oversize 20)
      - Irish washerwoman, full score, vellums; parts, handwritten (Oversize 20)
      - Oh Jeannie / Oh Jeanie, there's naething to fear ye, parts, handwritten; vocal score, copies (Oversize 20)
      - Oh what a beautiful city, full score, handwritten (Oversize 20)
      - Ohara Bushi, full score, handwritten; parts, handwritten (Oversize 20)
      - The Riddle, full score, vellums; full score, handwritten copy, incomplete; 2 folders (Oversize 20)
      - Scarborough fair, full score, handwritten; parts, handwritten; piano vocal, handwritten copy; piano score, handwritten (Oversize 20)
      - Scarlet Ribbons, vellums, possibly full score or possibly parts of several scores (Oversize 20)
      - Sweet Betsey, full score, handwritten; full score, vellums; parts, vellum (Oversize 21)
      - Waly Waly [The water is wide], full score, handwritten; parts, handwritten; piano vocal score, handwritten; piano vocal score, copy; miscellaneous sketches (Oversize 21)
      - Miscellaneous (Oversize 21)
        The red rosy bush (full score, handwritten with heavy annotations; handwritten copy of later version)
        Take 5 (cut/paste of printed copy)
        Trav'lin blues (handwritten copy, sketch)
        Varmeland (choral score, handwritten)
        Waltzing Matilda (piano vocal, handwritten)
    - Good Cheer
      - Full score, mix of handwritten and vellum (Oversize 21)
      - Full score, computer printout (Oversize 21)
      - Parts, mix of handwritten and vellums (Oversize 21)
      - Compositional sketches, handwritten (Oversize 21)
    - Greensleeves Fantasia (subset of A Festival Carols)
      See also Festival of Carols, above.
      - Parts, handwritten (Oversize 21)
      - Parts, copied (Oversize 21)
    - Jazz Mass for Saint Peter's
      - Composer's notes, including vision for staging (Oversize 22)
      - Full score, copied and bound ("Conductor's score") (Oversize 22)
      - Full score, bound and marked (Oversize 40)
      - Full score, vellums (Oversize 22)
      - Full score, copied (incomplete), possibly female soloist's copy as those parts are highlighted (Oversize 22)
      - Choral reduction, 10 copies; 9 are identical copies but with different markings, the 10th is different up until p. 51-52); 6 folders (Box 3)
      - Parts, vellum (Oversize 22)
      - Parts, handwritten (soprano sax only) (Oversize 22)
      - Parts, copied and marked (Oversize 22)
      - Parts, mix of different copies, some with notes (Oversize 22)
    - O Holy Night [Cantique de Noel] (subset of A Festival Carols)
      - Full score, copied, includes extra copies of a few pages (Oversize 22)
      - Choral manuscript, copies, some with markings (Oversize 41)
      - Parts, copied (Oversize 22)
      - Piano vocal, paste-up and several copies, including one with additional page at start (Oversize 22)
    - O Tannenbaum (subset of A Festival Carols)
      - Choral score manuscript, copies (Oversize 23)
      - Octavo, partial (Oversize 23)
      - Parts, copies (Oversize 23)
    - Old Folks Quadrille [title in donor inventory is "Stephen Foster Quadriled Orchestrations"]
      - Choral score, copied and bound (Oversize 23)